Guide to the Colgate Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Colgate Family papers
1752-1875
MS 144
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(3 boxes, 1 folio)
Letters, diaries, account books, financial and legal papers and memorabilia of the Davies, Brasher, Craig and related families, based in New York City. The business documents relate to the Atlantic trade (1788-1814) and comprise, among other records, receipts for the purchase of slaves in Jamaica in 1801. The diaries and account books in the collection include the family expense book (1739-1819) of Helen Kortright Brasher, a diary kept by Judith Brasher in 1766, extracts from a journal of a cruise in a privateer (1813), a diary (1837-1848) possibly belonging to Robert Colgate II, and a journal (1856-1858) of a voyage to China. Among the genealogical information is a biography of Helena Kortright Brasher written by Craig Colgate, Jr.
Colgate family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Craig Colgate, Craig Colgate, Jr., and Mrs. James G. Cannon between 1955 and 1979.
Scope and Contents
The Colgate Family Papers, 1752-1874, consist of letters, diaries, account books, and miscellaneous financial and legal papers of the Davies, Brasher, Craig, and other related families centered in New York City. They document both personal relations and business matters, the latter connected with the Atlantic trade and with land sales in western Virginia. Much of the information about business is in correspondence between members of these families. These are the principal components of the papers:
legal and financial papers, 1752-1794, of Benjamin Davies (1728-7) and his wife, Elizabeth (Wessells) Davies (d. 1794).
diary, 1766, of Judith (Gasherie) Brasher (1700-1772).
family expense book, 1773-1791, of Helen (Kortright) Brasher (1739-1819).
letters of John Pintard (1759-1844) and John Marsden Pintard, 1783-1799, to their. kinsmen, Elias Boudinot (1740-1821) and Elisha Boudinot (1749-1819). John Marsden Pintard's letters from Madeira, 1783-1785, contain commercial and political news. John Pintard's earliest letter, 1783, shows him apprehensive about a mercantile career.
miscellaneous papers, 1793-1801, of Samuel Craig (1757?-1802). Craig was buying land in western Virginia.
correspondence, account books, and legal and financial papers, 1796-1814, of Abraham Kortright Brasher (1777-1814). Brasher wrote to his brother, Gasherie Brasher (b. 1773), from Lisbon in 1798; to his sister, Helen Kortright (Brasher) Craig (1777-1853), from New Orleans in 1801; and to several persons from "Drondheim" [Trondheim?] in 1813. He received letters from business associates while doing business in New Orleans (1801-1803) and New York. The financial papers include receipts for the purchase of slaves in Jamaica in 1801 and documents related to the British seizure of the brig Harriot in 1804.
letters and business papers, 1805-1855, of Samuel Davies Craig (1785-1856). Craig exchanged many letters with his wife, Helen Kortright (Brasher) Craig (1777-1853), and his son, Benjamin Davies Craig (1808-1879), and he pursued his father's land interests in Virginia in the late 1810s and the late 1840s.
extracts from a journal, 1813, of a cruise in the privateer Scourge, commanded by Samuel G. Nicoll.
diary, 1837-1848, possibly by Robert Colgate II (1812-1885).
journal, 1856-1857, of a voyage to China.
For more biographical and genealogical information, see Helena Kortright Brasher, 1739-1819, by Craig Colgate, Jr., which is the first item in the papers, and typed genealogical notes filed with it.
The loose papers and the volumes are arranged in separate chronological sequences. The volumes are in three chronological sequences to conform to different sizes of containers. Most items have been cataloged individually in the department's manuscript catalog.
The Colgate Family Papers were given to Yale University Library by the estate of Craig Colgate, Craig Colgate, Jr., and Mrs. James G. Cannon between 1955 and 1979.
A receipt book of Benjamin Davies has been transferred to the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library because it contains a receipt written and signed by Button Gwinnett.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Business; Families; Shipping; New York (State); Southern States; United States -- Commerce; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Account books; Diaries; Brasher, Abraham Kortright, 1777-1814; Brasher, Helen Kortright, 1739-1819; Brasher, Judith Gasherie, 1700-1772; Craig, Benjamin Davies, 1808-1879; Craig, Helen Kortright Brasher, 1777-1853; Craig, Samuel Davies, 1785-1856; Craig, Samuel, 1757-1802; Pintard, John Marsden, -1811; Pintard, John, 1759-1844; Brashears family; Craig family; Davis family
- Inventory, 1752-(1766-1855)-1875; 1.5' (3 boxes, 1 folio)
  - Craig Colgate, Jr.: Helena Kortright Brasher, 1739-1819 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Genealogical notes and clipping, 1854, 1880, n.d (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous papers
    - 1752, 1754, 1762-1768 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Oversized deeds, 1762-1765, undated (Box 5)
    - 1772-1774 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Oversized deed, 1774 July 13 (Box 5)
    - 1775-1778 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Oversized deed, 1777 April 9 (Box 5)
    - 1783-1785 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Oversized deed, 1783 April 2 (Box 5)
    - 1790-1794 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1795-1797 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Oversized survey report of land in Kinawa County, 1795 July 24 (Box 5)
    - 1798-1799 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1800 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1801 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Oversized deed, 1801 March 11 (Box 5)
    - 1802 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1803 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1804-1806 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1807-1809 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1810-1813 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1814 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1815, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1819 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Oversized deed, 1819 (Box 5)
    - 1820-1821 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1823, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1829-1831 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 1834-1836 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - 1839 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 1840-1842 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - 1844-1847 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - 1848-1855, 1867, 1874-1875 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Judith (Gasherie) Brasher: diary, 1766 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Samuel G. Nicoll: "Sketch extract of Private Armed Schooner Scourge's Journal - Saml. G. Nicoll Esqre Commander", 1813 May 26-October 29 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - [Robert Colgate?]: diary, 1837-1848 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Journal of the Voyage to China in the N. B. Palmer", 1856 August 2- 1857 April 12 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Button Gwinnett: will (photograph), undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Blank certificates to promise receipt of, and payment for, "Deferred Stock of the United States", 179- (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Gasherie Brasher: autographed wallet inscribed to Abraham Kortright Brasher, 1796-1797 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Abraham Kortright Brasher
    - Petty cash book, 1796-1798 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Disbursement book, 1801-1806 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Waste book, 1803-1810 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Probated will, 1815 March 21 (Box 5)
    - Financial memorandum and commonplace book, 1809-1811 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Helen Kortright (Brasher) Craig: commonplace and memorandum book, 1809 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Samuel Davies Craig: receipt book, 1811-1842 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Monthly receipt book, 1815-1818 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Ann Wagstaff [and others?]: geography and history notebook, 1817, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Memorandum book, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Certificate of Benjamin D. K. Craig to practice law, 1828 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Helen (Kortright) Brasher: family expense book with receipts, recipes, and other papers laid in, 1773-1774, 1781-1786, 1789-1791, undated (Box 4)
  - "A Statement of the Division of the Brigantine Mary & Cargo a Prize to the private armed Schooner Benjamin Franklin ..." (found in Abraham Brasher's waste book), [1812?] (Box 4)
  - "Brasher Family Records," containing:
    - Genealogical information, 1663-1775 (part in Dutch), undated (Box 4)
    - Col. Abraham Brasher's pass allowing him to cross American lines to attend the New York State Convention at Fishkill, 1776 (Box 4)